Finding Aid for Dept. of Sociology (University of Michigan) records 1929-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dept. of Sociology (University of Michigan) records 1929-1987, 1950-1980
University of Michigan. Dept. of Sociology.
8 linear feet
Instructional and research unit in the College of Literature, Science and Art of University of Michigan Annual reports; budget files; executive committee minutes and records of other department committees; course evaluations; files relating to establishment, dissolution, and evaluations of programs; and faculty evaluations.
87160 Bimu C26 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were transferred from the Department of Sociology (Donor No. 6039 ) in 1977 and 1990.
The records are open for research.
While courses with sociological themes had been offered at the University of Michigan within the Departments of Political Science, Political Economy, and Philosophy since the early 1880s, the first courses bearing the name "sociology" were taught by Charles Horton Cooley in 1894. Cooley achieved a national reputation as one of the foremost sociologists of his day and was elected president of the American Sociological Society in 1918.
Despite the growth in course offerings and faculty during the 1920s, sociology courses continued to be offered within the Department of Economics until 1931. In that year, a separate Department of Sociology was created and Roderick Duncan McKenzie became the first chairman. McKenzie's own interests were in the field of human ecology and he was instrumental in setting up an ongoing seminar on the Detroit metropolitan community. McKenzie died in 1940 and was succeeded by Robert Cooley Angell. During the 1940s, the department maintained a close relationship with the University of Chicago and a number of prominent sociologists from that school also taught at the University of Michigan as visiting lecturers.
At the end of World War II, Dr. Rensis Likert and a team of social psychologists were invited to Ann Arbor to establish a survey research center which, in 1948, became the Institute for Social Research. Their arrival had a twofold impact on the Department of Sociology. First, a close working relationship developed between the two units. Several members of the team were given part-time teaching positions in the department and graduate students were able to use the extensive data gathered by these researchers for their doctoral dissertations. Second, the presence of these noted social psychologists provided the momentum for the creation of one of the nation's first doctoral programs in Social Psychology in 1947. Theodore Newcomb was selected as the program's first director. Organized as an interdepartmental program, students were required to take courses in both the Departments of Sociology and Psychology. Although the program proved highly successful in attracting students and in achieving national recognition, it was dissolved in 1967. The reasons for ending the program appear to include administrative problems, disagreements over curriculum and divergent theoretical interests in the two departments. Since 1967, students have been able to concentrate on social psychology within either department but joint degrees are no longer given.
In 1952, Amos H. Hawley became chairman of the department. The 1950s and early 1960s saw the creation of a number of new programs either organized by the department or affiliated with it. In 1951, the Detroit Area Study was established. A practicum for first-year graduate students, this ongoing survey program was designed to generate useful interview data and to train graduate students in the use of that data. In 1960, the Center for Research in Social Organization was established within the department. Designed to bring together those in the department whose research focused on changes in social organization, especially within a historical context, the Center flourished during the 1970s especially under the direction of Charles Tilly. In 1961, the Population Studies Center was established outside of the department but with the participation of a number of the department's faculty. The Center coordinated studies of changing fertility rates around the world as well as population distribution in the United States.
The department had five chairmen during the 1960s and 1970s: Guy E. Swanson (1961-1964); Albert E. Reiss (1964-1970); Howard Schuman (1970-1974); William Gamson (1974-1978); and Reynolds Farley (1978-1980). By the mid-1970s, it was clear just how much the department had expanded from the immediate post war years. There were three times as many courses given in 1975 as there were in 1945. In that same time period, more than six times the number of doctorates were awarded and the departmental budget rose six-fold. Outside research grants to departmental faculty which totalled only a few thousand dollars in 1945 had risen to $650,000 in 1975. Nevertheless, faculty turnover was unusually high. From 1962 to 1975, six senior faculty members resigned to accept positions at other universities and during the subsequent ten years several others followed. In a 1979 draft of the history of the department, Robert Cooley Angell noted that, despite increases in funding, the budget crunch at the University of Michigan was clearly a factor in the high turnover rate (see Executive Committee minutes of January 23, 1980, Box 5).
The records of the Department of Sociology document the administrative history of the department from 1929 to 1987, especially for the years 1950 to 1980. Records prior to 1950 and research records of individual faculty members are not well represented. The records are divided into six series: Annual Reports; Budgets; Committees; Course Evaluations; Establishment, Dissolution, and Evaluations of Programs; and Faculty Evaluations. Of these, the annual reports and the committee records are the most important for understanding the development of the department.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Center for Research in Social Organization.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Psychology.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Sociology.; University of Michigan. Doctoral Program in Social Psychology.
- Annual Reports (title varies)
  The Annual Reports series (0.5 linear feet) provides a yearly overview of the state of the department from 1955 to 1980. The title of these reports changed over the years. They were first called annual conferences or retreats, then committee reports, and finally annual reports. These records include the chairman's annual report as well as annual reports of various committees, programs, centers, and laboratories within the department.
  - 1955-1969, 27 folders (Box 1)
- Photographs 1959 (Box 1)
- Budgets
  The Budgets series (0.25 linear feet) contains general information regarding the department's annual budgets from 1968 to 1979 and specific information regarding merit pay increases for individual faculty members. Since the explanations for merit pay raises are sometimes viewed as de facto evaluations, folders in this series are closed for 30 years from date of creation.
  - 1968 (Box 8)
  - 1969 (Box 8)
  - 1970 (Box 8)
  - 1971 (Box 8)
  - 1972 (Box 8)
  - 1973 (Box 8)
  - 1974 (Box 8)
  - 1975 (Box 8)
  - 1976 (Box 8)
  - 1977 (Box 8)
  - 1978 (Box 8)
  - 1979 (Box 8)
- Committees
  Committees (4 linear feet) includes the records of the Executive Committee as well as those of several smaller and more temporary committees. The executive committee records provide the most complete source for documenting the history of the department. The minutes (1949-1980), which were assembled over the years in large notebooks, include not only the minutes of executive committee meetings but also correspondence, reports, committee agendas, announcements, and miscellaneous material broadly pertaining to executive committee business. The resulting records, especially for more recent years, provide a near daily log of departmental activities. Besides the minutes, the executive committee records also include six folders of memoranda (1938-1984).
  This series also contains correspondence and memoranda of several other committees, most of which were of a temporary nature. They include: the Ad Hoc Committee for the Curriculum in Social Organization (1964-1966); the Committee on Undergraduate Education (1952-1977); the Department Chairman Search Committee (1970-1977); and the Student-Faculty Committee (1955-1963). The Committee on Undergraduate Education was more long-standing than the others and these records provide some insight into the changing nature of the sociology curriculum. The Department Chairman Search Committee folder is rather thin and offers only limited information regarding the selection process.
  - Ad Hoc Committee for the Curriculum in Social Organization 1964-1966 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Undergraduate Education 1952-1977 (Box 1)
  - Department Chairman Search Committee 1970-1977 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee
    - "Constitution and By-Laws and Manual of Administrative Policies and Procedures" 1969 (Box 1)
    - Memoranda 1938-1984, 6 folders (Box 1)
    - Minutes
      - 1949-1967, 13 folders (Box 2)
      - 1968-1971, 8 folders (Box 3)
      - 1972-May 1977, 10 folders (Box 4)
      - August 1977-1980, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Student-Faculty Committee 1955-1963 (Box 5)
- Course Evaluations
  Course Evaluations (0.25 linear feet) includes quantitative summaries of student evaluations of sociology courses and faculty responses to those evaluations for the years 1955 to 1966. After 1966, course evaluations are included in the folders of specific faculty members in the series Faculty Evaluations.
  - 1955-1966, 4 folders (Box 5)
- Establishment, Dissolution, and Evaluations of Programs
  The series Establishment, Dissolution, and Evaluation of Programs (1 linear foot) chronicles the evolution of various key programs within the department. There are also evaluations of the department as a whole, including the final report from an internal review conducted in 1987. More than half of the series pertains to the Doctoral Program in Social Psychology and especially the dissolution of the program in 1967. Researchers interested in this subject should note that the last folder in this series contains a printed booklet entitled, "Proceedings of the Conference on Graduate Training in Social Psychology" (conference held at the University of Michigan, October 29, 1966) which includes comments of faculty and students regarding the program. This series also contains early correspondence regarding the establishment of the Center for Research in Social Organization.
  - Center for Research in Social Organization 1956-1961 (Box 5)
  - Department of Sociology
    - Correspondence and reports 1972-1976 (Box 5)
      (includes scattered materials regarding evaluations of the department)
    - Internal review (final report) April, 1987 (Box 5)
  - Doctoral Program in Social Psychology (joint program with the Department of Psychology)
    - Chronological files
      - 1952-1966, 20 folders (Box 5)
      - 1967-1976, 17 folders (Box 6)
    - "Proceedings of the Conference on Graduate Training in Social Psychology" (University of Michigan, October 29, 1966) (Box 6)
- Faculty Evaluations
  Faculty Evaluations (2 linear feet) contains evaluations of specific faculty members for promotion from 1922 to 1983. Folders listed under the names of department chairmen frequently contain evaluations of other faculty rather than evaluations of the chairman himself. Folders in this series are closed for 30 years from date of creation. The series has been divided into open files (those older than 30 years) and closed files. The finding aid includes the dates for opening of closed files.
  - Aberle, David S. 1951-1968, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Andreas, Carol 1967 (Box 6)
  - Angell, Robert C. 1940-1983, 5 folders (Box 6)
  - Beck, Elwood 1972-1974 (Box 6)
  - Blalock, Hubert 1954-1964 (Box 6)
  - Blood, Robert O. 1962-1966 (Box 6)
  - Carr, Lowell J. 1929-1958, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Cohen, Lillian 1950-1957 (Box 6)
  - Colver, Andrew 1966 (Box 6)
  - Conner, Walter 1970-1975, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Crecine, J.P. 1964-1972 (Box 7)
  - Duncan, O.D. 1970 (Box 7)
  - Eidson, Bettye K. 1972 (Box 7)
  - Feldman, Kenneth 1966 (Box 7)
  - Flynn, Michael S. 1970-1974 (Box 7)
  - Freedman, Ronald 1971-1976 (Box 7)
  - Friedell, Morris F. 1964-1969 (Box 7)
  - Fuller, Richard C. 1937-1943 (Box 7)
  - Gamson, William A. 1963-1976, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Gerstl, Joel 1958-1959 (Box 7)
  - Gilmore, Harlen W. 1953-1955 (Box 7)
  - Hawley, Amos 1937-1976, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Hodge, Robert W. 1969 (Box 7)
  - Holmes, Roy H. 1922-1949 (Box 7)
  - Howard, Leslie 1969 (Box 7)
  - Iversen, Gudmund 1970-1971 (Box 7)
  - Janowitz, Morris 1951-1960 (Box 7)
  - Laumann, Edward O. 1968-1972 (Box 7)
  - Lenski, Gerhard E. 1949-1965 (Box 7)
  - Linkert, Rensis 1956-1963 (Box 7)
  - Mayer, Thomas F. 1968-1969 (Box 7)
  - Mayhew, Leon 1969 (Box 7)
  - Miner, Horace 1969-1973 (Box 7)
  - Moch, Michael 1973-1975 (Box 7)
  - Moore, James C. 1968-1970 (Box 7)
  - Ostafin, Peter A. 1939-1957 (Box 7)
  - Palmore, James 1965-1970 (Box 7)
  - Redlinger, Lawrence 1969-1975 (Box 7)
  - Reiss, Albert 1959-1972 (Box 7)
  - Segal, David R. 1965-1974, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Sharp, Harry P. 1955-1961 (Box 7)
  - Silver, Allan 1954-1964 (Box 7)
  - Smith, Thomas 1966-1969 (Box 7)
  - Somers, Robert 1948-1967 (Box 7)
  - Street, David 1972-1974 (Box 7)
  - Swanson, Guy E. 1949-1970, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Truzzi, Marcello 1968-1970 (Box 7)
  - Ventimiglia, Joseph 1973-1974 (Box 7)
  - Wilson, Everett 1957-1966 (Box 7)
  - Wood, Arthur 1926-1960, 2 folders (Box 7)